<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.8" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="group__ieee802154" kind="group">
    <compoundname>ieee802154</compoundname>
    <title>IEEE 802.15.4 and Thread APIs</title>
    <innergroup refid="group__ieee802154__driver">IEEE 802.15.4 Drivers</innergroup>
    <innergroup refid="group__ieee802154__l2">IEEE 802.15.4 L2</innergroup>
    <innergroup refid="group__ieee802154__mgmt">IEEE 802.15.4 Net Management</innergroup>
    <innergroup refid="group__openthread">OpenThread stack</innergroup>
    <briefdescription>
<para>IEEE 802.15.4 native and OpenThread L2, configuration, management and driver APIs. </para>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para><simplesect kind="since"><para>1.0 </para>
</simplesect>
<simplesect kind="version"><para>0.8.0</para>
</simplesect>
</para>
<para>The IEEE 802.15.4 and Thread subsystems comprise the OpenThread L2 subsystem, the native IEEE 802.15.4 L2 subsystem (&quot;Soft&quot; MAC), a mostly vendor and protocol agnostic driver API shared between the OpenThread and native L2 stacks (&quot;Hard&quot; MAC and PHY) as well as several APIs to configure the subsystem (shell, net management, Kconfig, devicetree, etc.).</para>
<para>The <bold>OpenThread subsystem API</bold> integrates the external <ulink url="https://openthread.io">OpenThread</ulink> stack into Zephyr. It builds upon Zephyr&apos;s native IEEE 802.15.4 driver API.</para>
<para>The <bold>native IEEE 802.15.4 subsystem APIs</bold> are exposed at different levels and address several audiences:<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>shell (end users, application developers):<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>a set of IEEE 802.15.4 shell commands (see <computeroutput>shell&gt; ieee802154 help</computeroutput>)</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>application API (application developers):<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>IPv6, DGRAM and RAW sockets for actual peer-to-peer, multicast and broadcast data exchange between nodes including connection specific configuration (sample coming soon, see <ulink url="https://github.com/linux-wpan/wpan-tools/tree/master/examples">https://github.com/linux-wpan/wpan-tools/tree/master/examples</ulink> for now which inspired our API and therefore has a similar socket API),</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Kconfig and devicetree configuration options (net config library extension, subsystem-wide MAC and PHY Kconfig/DT options, driver/vendor specific Kconfig/DT options, watch out for options prefixed with IEEE802154/ieee802154),</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Network Management: runtime configuration of the IEEE 802.15.4 protocols stack at the MAC (L2) and PHY (L1) levels (see <ref refid="group__ieee802154__mgmt" kindref="compound">IEEE 802.15.4 Net Management</ref>),</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>L2 integration (subsystem contributors):<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>see <ref refid="group__ieee802154__l2" kindref="compound">IEEE 802.15.4 L2</ref></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>implementation of Zephyr&apos;s internal L2-level socket and network context abstractions (context/socket operations, see <ref refid="group__net__l2" kindref="compound">Network L2 Abstraction Layer</ref>),</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>protocol-specific extension to the interface structure (see <ref refid="group__net__if" kindref="compound">Network Interface abstraction layer</ref>)</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>protocol-specific extensions to the network packet structure (see <ref refid="group__net__pkt" kindref="compound">Network Packet Library</ref>),</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>OpenThread and native IEEE 802.15.4 share a common <bold>driver API</bold> (driver maintainers/contributors):<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>see <ref refid="group__ieee802154__driver" kindref="compound">IEEE 802.15.4 Drivers</ref></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>a basic, mostly PHY-level driver API to be implemented by all drivers,</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>several &quot;hard MAC&quot; (hardware/firmware offloading) extension points for performance critical or timing sensitive aspects of the protocol </para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
    </detaileddescription>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
